Teper, Lazare. Collection. 6036/030
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Teper, Lazare. Collection
1928-1979
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Teper, Lazare
International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union
6036/030
1.5 cubic feet
1.5 linear ft.
Articles, reprints, pamphlets, correspondence, photographs.
This collection contains reports and statements written or delivered by Lazare Teper, as well as correspondence and notes relating to a course, "Labor Issues and the Planning Process," taught by Teper.
5770062
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183 kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel
Compiled by:
Kheel Staff, August 30, 2011
EAD encoding:
Kathryn Dowgiewicz, January 10, 2013
Biographical / Historical
Founded in 1900 by local union delegates representing about 2,000 members in cities in the northeastern United States, the ILGWU grew in geographical scope, membership size, political influence to become one of the most powerful forces in American organized labor by mid-century. Representing workers in the women's garment industry, the ILGWU worked to improve working and living conditions of its members through collective bargaining agreements, training programs, health care facilities, cooperative housing, educational opportunities, and other efforts. In 1995, the ILGWU merged with the Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers Union (ACTWU) to form the Union of Needletrades, Industrial and Textile Employees (UNITE).
Biographical / Historical
Lazare Teper was born in Odessa, Russia on January 16, 1908, and after studying at the University of Paris, he came to the United States in 1927. Teper received both his masters and doctorate degrees in economics from Johns Hopkins University in 1930 and 1931. He held research assistant positions before becoming research director of the ILGWU New York Dress Joint Board in 1935. In 1937, Teper headed the newly formed Research Department at the union's General Office and was the director until his retirement in 1980. Under his guidance, the department gained wider respect in government, academic, business and labor circles.
Teper played a key role in developing policies and regulations under the legislative acts created in the 1930s, which included social security, unemployment insurance and minimum wage laws. As the import threat worsened, he devoted more time to trade issues. In 1956, Teper was advisor to the U.S. delegation that negotiated the first agreement with Japan regulating apparel and textile imports.
During his career, Teper was a consultant and advisor to numerous U.S. delegations negotiating textile multilateral or bilateral agreements. He also was a member of many committees and served as a delegate for national and international conferences. He wrote and published reports and articles on labor, employment, income and statistics. Teper was active in several professional societies including the American Statistical Association, the American Economic Association, the Industrial Relations Research Association, the American Association for the Advancement of Science, and the Metropolitan Economic Association. After his retirement, he served as director of ILGWU special projects, focusing on issues such as the federal minimum wage and homework. Teper died on April 25, 1985.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of reports and documents created for and during Lazare Teper's tenure as Director of the ILGWU Research Department. General items included are various notes from seminars and meetings he attended, lists of brainstorming topics or ideas, copies of pages from address and note books and correspondence. There is correspondence and information for the 1969 conference "Labor Issues and the Planning Process" which Teper was involved. Teper was part of a mission to Mexico to study that country's income distribution and economic policies. During the research, individuals were interviewed and documents and statistics studied. His report investigated the shifts in income distribution and its relationship to changes in minimum wage and protective labor legislation in Mexico. The records contain all of his work and research that went into the report. Another interesting study is a comprehensive investigation of the strike of the Yellow Cab Company in Baltimore that took place November 6-13, 1928.
The majority of the material centers on articles written and reports compiled by Teper and are arranged by year. Articles and reports include "Forty-Cent Minimum Wage for the Women's Clothing Industry," "Aspects of Industrial Homework in Apparel Trades," "Observations on the Cost of Living Index of the Bureau of Labor Statistics," "Wage-Price Issues 1948," "The Function of Management in Achieving Sound Labor Relations," and "Basic Trends in the Women's Garment Industry." Reports focus on topics such as the minimum wage, amendments to the Fair Labor Standards Act, statistics and price indexes, unemployment, economic conditions of the garment industry and the impact of imports. Teper also often presented speeches and remarks at meetings and conferences which are also contained in the records. He delivered numerous statements on behalf of the ILGWU to Senate and House Committees and Sub-Committees including Economic, Labor and Education, Appropriations, Ways and Means, and Trade and Tariff Commissions, which are organized according to year.
The records also provide biographical information as well as remembrances and correspondence following his death. While the collection contains Teper's personal records, also pertinent are the related collections at the Kheel Center of the ILGWU Research Department: Research Department Records 1921-1983 (5780/105), Research Department Records 1884-1948 (5780/045), Research Department Records 1907-1980 (5780/123), Research Department Records 1907-1948 (5780/056), Research Department Records 1890-1971 (5780/168), Research Department Records 1945-1995 (5780/209), Research Department Reports 1938-1985 (5780/078), Research Department U.S. National Industry Recovery Administration (NIRA) Hearing Files 1933-1937 (5780/163), and the Research Department Wages and Hours Files 1938-1942, 1950-1975 (5780/148).
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related Collections: 5780: ILGWU records 5780/105: ILGWU. Research Department records 5780/045: ILGWU. Research Department records 5780/123: ILGWU. Research Department records 5780/056: ILGWU. Research Department collected documents 5780/168: ILGWU. Research Department records 5780/209: ILGWU. Research Department records 5780/078: ILGWU. Research Department reports 5780/163: ILGWU. Research Department. United States NIRA hearing records 5780/148: ILGWU. Research Department wages and hours files
Women's clothing industry -- United States.; Labor unions -- Clothing workers -- United States.; Clothing workers -- United States.; Industrial relations -- United States.; Teper, Lazare, -- 1908-; International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union.; International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union. -- Research Dept.
5770062
- Biographical information (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Notes, 1954-1967 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  Scope and Contents
  Also includes undated material.
- Correspondence, 1948-1954 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  Includes letter from David Dubinsky.
- Labor Issues and the Planning Process [Folder 1 of 2], 1967-1970 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  Correspondence and notes relating to course taught by Teper.
- Labor Issues and the Planning Process [Folder 2 of 2], 1967-1971 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Memoriam, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Reports and Statements, 1929 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  Includes: Strike, Yellow Cab Company, Baltimore, Maryland, November 6-13, 1928.
- Reports and Statements, 1932 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  Includes: Elections in Soviet Russia.
- Reports and Statements, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  Includes: Russia's Clerical Workers; Handkerchief Industry: Preliminary Report.
- Reports and Statements, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  Includes: Forty-Cent Minimum Wage for the Women's Clothing Industry.
- Reports and Statements, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  Includes: Aspects of Industrial Homework in Apparel Trades (with Nathan Weinberg).
- Reports and Statements, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  Includes: Observations on the Cost of Living Index of the Bureau of Labor Statistics.
- Reports and Statements, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  Includes: Notes on the Indexes of Unit Labor Costs of the Bureauf of Labor Statistics.
- Reports and Statements, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  Includes: Management and Labor Make Strong Medicine; Wage Dilemma, 1947; Statement before the House Labor Sub-Committee.
- Reports and Statements, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  Includes: Wage-Price Issues, 1948; Memorandum submitted to New Jersey Unemployment Compensation Commission; Memorandum on the Testimony of Dr. John V. Van Sickle; This Thing Called Productivity; Statement before the Senate Labor Sub-Committee; L'arbitage des conflicts de travail aux Etats-Unis; Union Access to Employers' Records in U.S.
- Reports and Statements, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  Includes: Basic Trends in the Women's Garment Industry; Prospects in Women's Apparel Industry; What Is An Executive Worth?; "Motivation Analysis in Market Reseach"--A Criticism; Statement before the Subcommittee on Study of Monopoly Power; The Function of Management in Achieving Sound Labor Relations; Statement before the House Committee on Education and Labor; Revenues of Trade Unions in the U.S.; The Mental Arithmetic of Messrs. Schreider and Wood (or sad reflections of some statistical thinking).
- Reports and Statements, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  Includes: Reviews from the Industrial and Labor Relations Review; The Effect of Multi-Industry Employment on the Industrial Distribution of Wages.
- Reports and Statements, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  Includes: Seasonal Fluctuations in Employment in the Women's Clothing Industry in New York.
- Reports and Statements, 1952 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  Includes: Statement before the Wage Stabilization Board; Statement on Proposed Bill for State- Wide Minimum Wage; Comments on Edward Hollander's "Notes on the Revision of the CPI."
- Reports and Statements, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  Includes: Personnel Policy and Older Workers--An Overview
- Reports and Statements, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  Includes: Opening Remarks before the Joint Committee on the Economic Report; Statement Submitted to the Joint Committee on the Economic Report.
- Reports and Statements, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  Includes: BLS Consumers' Price Index and the AMS Index of Prices Paid by Farmers for Family Living--A Juxtaposition; The Social and Economic Implications of the Fair Labor Standards Act: An Interpretation in Terms of Social Cost; Proposed Statement Before the House Committee on Education and Labor (not delivered).
- Reports and Statements, 1957 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  Includes: Statement on the Relationshipo of Prices to Economic Stability and Growth; Prices and Steady Economic Growth: An issue in Public Policy Formulation.
- Reports and Statements, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  Includes: Statement before the Senate Subcommittee on Labor; Discussion from Annual Meeting of the Industrial Relations Research Association; Dissenting Opinion I the matter of the Report, Findings of Fact and Proposed Mandatory Decree submitted to the Minimum Wage Board; Statement before the Subcommittee to Investigate Problems of the Textile Industry; Measurement of Prices.
- Reports and Statements, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  Includes: Foreign Trade and Collective Bargaining: Discussion of the Arnow Paper; Comments onf the Report of the Price Statistics Review Committee of the national Bureau of Economic Research.
- Reports and Statements, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  Includes: Government Price Statistics; La securite syndicale aux Etats-Unis (with Daniel Nelson); Statement before the Subcommittee on the Impact of Imports and Exports on American Employment; Unemployment Statistics in a Changing Economy: The Labor View; Introductory Remarks to the Commentary on the Report of the Price Statistics Review Committee.
- Reports and Statements, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  Includes: Comments on the New York State Unemployment Insurance Program; Statement before the Senate Subcommittee to Investigate Problems of the Textile Industry.
- Reports and Statements, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  Includes: Review Brief before the United States Tariff Commission (with Milton Fried); Statement before the House Select Subcommittee on Labor; Brief before the Trade Information Committee.
- Reports and Statements, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  Includes: Statement on Amendments to the Fair Labor Standards Act; Discussion of Harry Malisoff's "Welfare and Social Insurance in a Great 'Society' and Robert J. Meyer's "What Risks and Which Groups Can Be Covered Under Social Insurance."
- Reports and Statements, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  Includes: Utilization of Price Indexes in Private and Public Policy Decision.
- Reports and Statements, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  Includes: Analysis of Economic Conditions of United States Apparel Industry and Present and Prospective Impact of Imports; Statement before the House Appropriations Subcommittee on the Departments of Labor, Health, Educatoin and Welfare.
- Reports and Statements, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  Includes: Statement to the Bureau of Labor Statistics; Domestic Apparel Industry: Economic Background and the Impact of Imports (with Milton Fried).
- Reports and Statements, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  Includes: The Consumer Price Index; Training Apparel Workers and Subsidies (with Milton Fried).
- Reports and Statements, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  Includes: Comments on the Report of the U.S. Tariff Commission "Economic Factors Affecting the Use of Items 807.00 and 806.30 of the Tariff Schedules of the United States"; Item 807.00 of the Tariff Schedules of the United States and the Apparel Industry.
- Reports and Statements, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  Includes: Imports: A Review; Resolution on Foreign Trade at ILGWU Convention.
- Reports and Statements, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  Includes: Statement on Trade Reform; Statement and Supplementary Statement on Proposed Increases in Unemployment, Workmen's Compensation and Disability Benefits.
- Reports and Statements, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  Includes: Politicization and Statistics; The Need to Preserve the Current Coverage of the Consumer Price Index for Urban Wage Earners and Clerical Workers; Testimony in re Hearings on Chapters 60-61 of Draft Conversion of the Tariff Schedules of the United States into the Format of the Brussels Tariff Nomenclature.
- Reports and Statements, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  Includes: The Impact of Duty Reductions on the Domestic Women's and Children's Apparel Industry; Apparel (Knit and Woven) Imports under the Provisions of Item 807.00 of the Tariff Schedules of the United States; The Domestic Women's and Children's Apparel Industry and Multilateral Trade Negotiations; Statements on Unemployment Insurance.
- Reports and Statements, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  Includes: Statement before Industry Committee No. 138A for Puerto Rico; Data Bearing on Economic Development of Puerto Rico.
- Reports and Statements, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  Includes: Observations on Productivity; Women's and Children's Apparel and the Multifiber Textile Arrangement; The Background and Shortcoming of the Multifiber Arrangement and the Bilateral Agreements Concluded Under its Provisions; Statement in the matter of Change from the "chief value" to the "chief weight" classification of textile imports.
- Reports and Statements, 1978-1979 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  Includes: Statement before the National Commission on Employment and Unemployment Statistics; Statement to the Secretary, Trade Policy Staff Committee; letter to the Editor I response to "Problems with Federal Economic Statistical System and Some Alternatives for Improvement."